Guide to the Edward John Kempf Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward John Kempf papers
1911-1972
MS 728
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(19 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, research materials, and personal papers of Edward J. Kempf, American psychiatrist, psychologist, author, and pioneer in the field of psychosomatic medicine. The papers consist primarily of various drafts of Kempf's articles and books and correspondence with other psychiatrists and psychologists relating to his work. Correspondents include William C. Menninger, Adolph Meyer, and Gardner Murphy.
Kempf, Edward J. (Edward John), 1885-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Edward J. Kempf, 1974.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings and Research Materials. III. Personal.
Biographical / Historical
Edward John Kempf (1885-1972), American psychiatrist, psychologist, psychopathologist and author, is known primarily for his pioneer work in the development of psychosomatic medicine and for his theory that the human personality is a product of biological evolution. He received an A. B. from Indiana University in 1907 and an M. D. from Western Reserve in 1910. From 1911-1912 he worked at Indianapolis State Hospital applying the Freudian passive free association method to the treatment of schizophrenic young women. According to Dr. Kempf's autobiographical notes:
"They were the first cases of schizophrenia (divided mind) treated by psychoanalytic methods in American psychiatric hospitals, who recovered from the disease and reintegrated normal egoistic self-control of social behavior with insight into causes of their emotional conditions. These cases directly controverted Freud's dogma that all cases of dementia praecox are incurable and progressively deteriorating."
Thus, Dr. Kempf was both early to use and to criticize Freudian teachings.
From 1912 to 1914 Dr. Kempf served as a staff physician at Phipps Psychiatric Clinic, at Johns Hopkins Hospital in Baltimore. In 1913 he married Helen Dorothy Clarke, a graduate of Johns Hopkins Medical School. Between 1914 and 1920 he served as a clinical psychiatrist at St. Elizabeth's Hospital in Washington, D. C. and, during this period, published Autonomic Functions and the Personality (1918). From 1920 to 1931 he engaged in private practice in New York and Santa Barbara.
In 1923 Dr. Kempf met with Sigmund Freud in the Austrian Tyrolean Alps. The two psychiatrists discussed their respective theories of the personality and methods of dealing with schizophrenia. In the Life and Confessions of a Psychologist (1923), G. Stanley Hall said of Freud and the young Kempf:
"Freud and his orthodox disciples concerned themselves solely with the psychic, ignoring the somatic structures and functions, which later Kempf, the only American who has done signal creative work in the field, has sought to supply."
Dr. Kempf consistently advocated a "more active method" (than the Freudian) of treating selected cases of emotional neuroses and psychoses and continued his systematic development of psychobiology. His research covered more than 2000 cases and dealt with the psychology of schizophrenia. Kempf used the sciences of biology, genetics, embryology, physiology, psychology, sociology, anthropology, physics and chemistry to explain his theory of the human personality as a product of biological evolution.
From 1931 until his death in 1972 Dr. Kempf was actively engaged in research and writing. His last book, Abraham Lincoln's Philosophy of Common Sense: An Analytical Biography of a Great Mind, was published in 1965.
Dr. Kempf was a member of a number of societies, including: the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Medical Association, the American Psychiatric Association, the American Psychoanalytic Society, the American Psychological Association, the American Psychopathological Association, the American Society for Psychical Research, the Cosmos Club, the New York Academy of Medicine, the New York Academy of Sciences, the Pavlovian Society of North America, and the Washington Psychoanalytic Society.
The collection is divided into three series. The CORRESPONDENCE series contains letters to and from Edward Kempf and spans the years 1912-1972. Unfortunately, a large part of Dr. Kempf's correspondence — including his correspondence with Sigmund Freud — apparently no longer exists. A significant amount of correspondence with psychologists and psychiatrists such as William C. Menninger, Adolph Meyer and Gardner Murphy remains. The WRITINGS AND RESEARCH MATERIALS series consists of published and unpublished articles by Dr. Kempf and drafts of manuscripts. The manuscripts are, successively, Evolution of the Personality (in four drafts); Bisexual Differentiation (in two drafts, a work which appears to be related to but separate from Evolution of the Personality ); and, Maturation of Man (in three drafts; Maturation of Man is a revision of Evolution of the Personality ).
The Edward J. Kempf Papers were the gift of Mrs. Edward J. Kempf in 1974.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, research materials, and personal papers of Edward J. Kempf, American psychiatrist, psychologist, author, and pioneer in the field of psychosomatic medicine. The papers consist primarily of various drafts of Kempf's articles and books and correspndence with other psychiatrists and psychologists relating to his work. Correspondents include William C. Menninger, Adolph Meyer, and Gardner Murphy.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Medicine, Psychosomatic; Psychiatry; Psychology; Psychiatrists; Psychologists; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982; Gantt, Horsley W.; Hall, G. Stanley (Granville Stanley), 1844-1924; Kempf, Edward J. (Edward John), 1885-1971; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974; Menninger, William Claire, 1899-1966; Meyer, Adolf, 1866-1950; Miner, Eunice Thomas; Murphy, Gardner, 1895-1979; Rosenzweig, Saul, 1907-2004; Yerkes, Robert M. (Robert Mearns), 1876-1956
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1912-1972; Series I; l linear feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The CORRESPONDENCE series is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the correspondent. Letters from Edward J. Kempf are filed under the last name of the addressee. The series consists almost entirely of letters except that articles by Edward J. Kempf have been left with the appropriate covering letter in the folders of Thomas E. Bamford, Jr., Godfrey Thompson, Adolph Meyer, Science, George H. Simmons, and [underline] White.
  - Ad - At (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adler, Alfred
    General
    See:
    G. Stanley Hall, box 1, folder 14
  - American Psychiatric Association
    Austin M. Davis, box 1, folder 5
    Philip Q. Roche, box 2, folder 32
    Harry J. Sullivan, box 2, folder 34
  - American Psychoanalytic Association
    LeRoy M. A. Maeder, box 1, folder 24
    George J. Mohr, box 1, folder 24
    Merrill Whitney, box 2, folder 42
    Emanuel Windholz, box 2, folder 42
  - American Psychopathological Association, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
    See also:
    L. E. Emerson, box 1, folder 7
    Fritz A. Freyhan, box 1, folder 9
    Nolan D. Lewis, box 1, folder 22
    Ross McChapman, box 1, folder 24
    Martin W. Peck, box 2, folder 31
  - American Psychosomatic Society
    William A. Greene, box 1, folder 11
  - American Society for Psychical Research
    Lydia W. Allison, box 1, folder 1
    Dorothy A. Buck, box 1, folder 2
    Laura Dale, box 1, folder 5
    George Hyslop, box 1, folder 18
    Mrs. Richard C. Kennedy, box 1, folder 20
    Gardner Murphy, box 1, folder 28
  - Association for the Advancement of Psychotherapy
    Emil A. Gutheil, box 1, folder 11
  - Ba - Bu (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barker, Lewellys F., 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
    To JWD/From JWD: (4/4)
  - Bleuler, M., 1950-1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    To JWD/From JWD: (6/3)
  - Ca - Cu (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cannon, Walter B., 1929-1930, 1936, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4A)
  - Da - Du (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Drever, James, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    To JWD/From JWD: (5/5)
    James Drever, box 1, folder 6
  - Eb - Em (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    To JWD/From JWD: (1/0)
  - Eliot, Thomas D., 1930-1931, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8A)
    To JWD/From JWD: (13/8)
  - Fe - Fu (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Freud, Anna, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Freud, Sigmund
    Ernest E. Hadley, box 1, folder 13
  - Ga - Gu (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gantt, W. Horsley, 1930, 1933, 1938,1941-1943, 1954-1955, 1957-1958, 1967, 1969-1970, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    To JWD/From JWD: (14/19)
  - Ha - Ho (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hall, G. Stanley, 1923, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    To JWD/From JWD: (4/0)
  - Hall, Roscoe, 1934-1935, 1938, 1941-1942, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hamilton, Samuel W., 1934-1935, 1943, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    To JWD/From JWD: (5/6)
  - Hefferline, Ralph F., 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    To JWD/From JWD: (5/3)
  - Hyslop, George H., 1941, 1947, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    To JWD/From JWD: (3/3)
  - Ja - Jo (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ka - Ku (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Kempf, Dorothy, 1919, 1923, 1931, 1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    To JWD/From JWD: (5/0)
  - Kuntz, Albert, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 21A)
    To JWD/From JWD: (2/3)
  - La - Lu (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lippmann, Walter, 1946, 1966-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    To JWD/From JWD: (7/3)
  - Ma - Mo (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - The Medical Society of the County of New York
    See: William L. Wheeler
  - The Medical Society of the State of New York
    See: Waring Willis
  - Menninger, William C., 1946, 1955, 1957-1958, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    To JWD/From JWD: (7/0)
  - Meyer, Adolph, 1912-1914, 1928, 1931, 1936-1937, 1941-1942, 1944-1946, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    To JWD/From JWD: (21/19)
    William Sheldon, box 2, folder 37
  - Miner, Eunice Thomas, 1939, 1952-1959, 1966, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    To JWD/From JWD: (17/13) See also: Edward Cohen
  - Murphy, Gardner, 1942, 1945-1947, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    To JWD/From JWD: (9/3)
  - Ne - Ni (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - New York Academy of Sciences
    Ralph F. Hefferline, box 1, folder 17
    Duncan A. MacInnes, box 1, folder 24
    Eunice T. Miner, box 1, folder 27
    Walter S. Root, box 2, folder 32
    William S. Taylor, box 2, folder 39
    Edward M. Weyer, box 1, folder 24
    Edgar W. White, box 2, folder 42
    Otto v. St. Whitelock, box 2, folder 42
  - New York Society for Clinical Psychiatry
    Frank J. Curran, box 1, folder 4
  - Ob - Ov (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Pa - Po (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Parapsychological Association
    Montague Ullman, box 2, folder 40
  - The Pavlovian Society of North America
    W. Horsley Grant, box 1, folder 12
  - Re - Ro (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Rosenweig, Saul, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    To JWD/From JWD: (6/5)
  - Sa - Su (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Science, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    To JWD/From JWD: (0/1)
  - Seligman, C. G., 1923-1924, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    To JWD/From JWD: (3/2)
  - Sheldon, William, 1942-1944, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Adolph Meyer, box 1, folder 26
  - Te - Tr (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Taylor, William S., 1943, 1945, 1948, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    To JWD/From JWD: (4/5)
  - Twelfth International Congress of Psychology
  - Ul (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Va - Ve (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Wa - Wo (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Washington Psychoanalytic Society
    Rex E. Buxton, box 1, folder 2
  - Yerkes, Robert M., 1932, 1936-1938, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Z (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 44)
- WRITINGS AND RESEARCH MATERIALS, 1911-1959; Series II; 7 linear feet (16 boxes)
  The WRITINGS AND RESEARCH MATERIALS series includes reprints of Edward J. Kempf's published articles, a number of unpublished articles, and an imperfect copy of his monograph, The Autonomic Functions and the Personality. The series consists primarily of drafts of manuscripts. The manuscripts are, successively, Evolution of the Personality (in four drafts); Bisexual Differentiation (in two drafts, a work which appears to be related to but separate from Evolution of the Personality ); and, Maturation of Man (in three drafts; Maturation of Man is a revision of Evolution of the Personality. In addition, one folder following the manuscripts contains references central to all drafts. A section of miscellaneous chapters and notes which do not seem to be a part of any manuscript completes the series.
  The series is arranged sequentially in the above order.
  - Published Articles
    - "Abraham Lincoln's Organic and Emotional Neurosis,", 1952 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "Abraham Lincoln's Physical Constitution, Personality and Mind,", undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - "The Autonomic Functions and the Personality,", 1918 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "Basic Biodynamics,", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - "The Behavior Chart in Mental Diseases,", 1915 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - "Biodynamics of Everyday Life,", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - "Bisexual Factors in Curable Schizophrenia,", 1949 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Charles Darwin — The Affective Sources of his Inspiration and Anxiety Neurosis, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - "Did Consciousness of Self Play a Part in the Behavior of this Monkey?,", 1916 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "The Integrative Functions of the Nervous System Applied to Some Reactions in Human Behavior, and their Attending Psychic Functions,", 1914 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - "The Law of Attitude,", 1945 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "The Mechanistic Classification of Neuroses and Psychoses Produced by Distortion of Autonomic-Affective Functions,", 1919 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "A Minimum Course in Psychopathology for Medical Students,", 1921 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - "Ontogeny of Bisexual Differentiation in Man,", 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "The Origin and Evolution of Bisexual Differentiation,", 1947 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Postural Tensions for Normal and Abnormal Human Behavior — Their Significance, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - "The Probable Origin of Man's Belief in Sympathetic Magic and Taboo,", 1931 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - "The Psychology of 'the Yellow Jacket'", 1917 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - "The Significance of the Plastic Bisexuality of Man for the Medical and Social Sciences,", 1942 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - "Suppression and Substitution as a Factor in Sex Differences,", 1913 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "The Tonus of Autonomic Segments as Causes of Abnormal Behavior,", 1920 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - "Two Methods of Subjective Learning in the Monkey Macacus Rhesus ", 1916 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - unpublished Articles
    - Debate with Dr. Landis re: schizophrenia, undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - "Essential Factors in the Physio-Psychology of Ego-Organization in Relation to Malignant Dissociation Neuroses,", [1935?] (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - "Evolution of Ego-Organization,", undated (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - "Paper Read Before the Medico-Psychological Society,", 1914 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - "Thesis,", [1913-1914?] (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - "The Unsane Treatment of our Insane Patients,", [1911-1912?] (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - "What I Believe About Immortality? Why?,", Circa 1935 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - untitled, undated (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Evolution of the Personality (1st draft)
    - Outline of the first draft of Evolution of the Personality, 1931-1938 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Chapter II, "Outline of Principles of Biological Evolution,", undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Chapter III, "Biological Origin, Functions and Evolution of the Pain-Pleasure-Pain Principle,", undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Chapter IV, "Organic Foundations of the Personality,", undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Chapter VI, "Significance of Integrative Actions of the Nervous System for the Personality,", undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Chapter VII, "The Principle of Organization of Reflexes to Maintain the Integrity of a Counterbalancing Organism versus the Theory of Instincts,", undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Chapter VIII, "Conditioned Reflexes in Relation to Organization of Personality and Attitudes,", undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Chapter IX, "Postural Tones - Attitudes,", undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Chapter X, "The Autonomic-Affective Dynamism,", undated (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Chapter XI, "The Autonomic Pressure of Energy and Feeling to Live,", undated (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Chapter XII, "The Ego Organization — Its Origin, Nature and Functioning,", undated (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Chapter XIII, "The Ego-Organization and its Mentation through Use of Representative Kinaesthesias,", undated (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Chapter XIV, "The Organized Attitude of the Organism Interactive with its Environmental Complex as the Personality,", undated (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Chapter XV, "The Socialization of Attitude Developing the Ego Organization,", undated (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Chapter XVIII, "Primacy of Self-Love,", undated (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Chapter XIX, "Adaptive Mechanisms of the Personality,", undated (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Chapter XX, "Sociogenic Workings of Attitude" (Part 1), undated (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Chapter XX, "Sociogenic Workings of Attitude" (Part 2), undated (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Evolution of the Personality (2nd draft)
    - Outline of the second draft of Evolution of the Personality, undated (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Introduction, "Understanding the Personality,", undated (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - Chapter I, "Basic Factors in the Organization of Life,", undated (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - Chapter I, "Basic Factors in Pyramiding Organization of Life,", 1946 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Chapter II, "The Cell as the Highest Unit of Life,", undated (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Chapter III, "Cell Reproduction,", undated (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Chapter IV, "Holistic Laws of Life,", undated (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - Chapter V, "Bidynamic Constitutional Differentiation of Organs,", undated (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - [Chapter VI?], "Evolution of Bisexual and Somatic Differentiation,", undated (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Chapter VII, "Gonadal Differentiation and Development of Sex Characters,", undated (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - Chapter VIII, "Interaction Between the Gonads and Other Endocrine Glands,", undated (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - Chapter IX, "Environmental Conditioning of Endocrine Interactions and Vitamin Intake,", undated (Box 9, Folder 104)
    - Chapter X, "Bisexual Internal and Environmental Adaptability of the Autogenous Pressure of Energy,", undated (Box 9, Folder 105)
    - Chapter XII, "The Integrative Levels of the Nervous System,", undated (Box 9, Folder 106)
    - Chapter XIII, "Physiopsychology of Autogenous Organization of Attitude,", undated (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Chapter XV, "Psychobiology of Autogenous, Counterbalancing, Neuro-Cardiovascular, Hemodynamic Emotivation,", undated (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Chapter XVI, "Autonomic Segmental Cravings Differentiating Attitudes,", 1943 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Evolution of the Personality (3rd draft)
    - Outline of the third draft of Evolution of the Personality, undated (Box 11, Folder 110)
    - Chapter I, "Understanding the Personality,", undated (Box 11, Folder 111)
    - Chapter II, "Biological Differentiation of Constitutional Energic Types,", undated (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - [Chapter III], "The Origin and Evolution of Sex,", undated (Box 11, Folder 113)
    - Chapter III, "Bisexuality of the Gonads and the Organism,", undated (Box 11, Folder 114)
    - Chapter IV, "Environmental and Gonadal Factors Influencing the Development and Differentiation of Sex,", undated (Box 11, Folder 115)
    - Chapter V, "Interaction Between the Gonads and Other Endocrine Glands,", undated (Box 11, Folder 116)
    - Chapter VI, "Bisexual Internal and Environmental Adaptability of the Autogenous Pressure of Energy,", undated (Box 11, Folder 117)
    - Chapter VII, "Bipotential Social Sexual Adaptability in Mammals,", undated (Box 11, Folder 118)
    - Chapter VIII, "Social Sexual Behavior of Infrahuman Primates,", undated (Box 11, Folder 119)
    - Chapter IX, "Comparative Primate Attitudinal Characteristics,", undated (Box 11, Folder 120)
    - Chapter X, "Phylogenetic Origins of Human Social Sexual Traits in Lower Primates,", undated (Box 11, Folder 121)
    - Chapter XI, "Human Perineal Anatomy, Physiology, and Psychology,", undated (Box 11, Folder 122)
    - Chapter XII, "The Biological Significance of Orgasm and Heterosexual Love,", undated (Box 11, Folder 123)
    - Chapter XIII, "Interactive Physiological, Psychological and Sociological Factors in the Organization of Functioning of the Organism into the Personality,", undated (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - Evolution of the Personality (4th draft)
    - Outline of the fourth draft of Evolution of the Personality, undated (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - "Introduction,", undated (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - Chapter II, "Pyramiding Levels of Electro-Physico-Chemical Organization,", undated (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - Chapter III, "The Second or Molecular Level of Autogenous Organization of Electromagnetic Energy,", undated (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Chapter IV, "Second or Atomic Level of Autogenous Organization of Equilibrating Interaction of Electromagnetic Energy,", undated (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - Chapter V, "Unorganized Physically Equilibrating Reversible Reaction Systems,", undated (Box 12, Folder 130)
    - Chapter VI, "Nonliving, Unorganized, Equilibrating, Bisensimotor, Reversible, Bidynamic, Self-Reproducing Reaction Systems,", undated (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - References central to all drafts, undated (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Bisexual Differentiation (1st draft)
    - Outline of Bisexual Differentiation, undated (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - Outline and Introduction to Bisexual Differentiation, undated (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Chapter I, "Thermodynamic Origin of Bisexual Differentiation,", undated (Box 13, Folder 135)
    - Chapter II, "Thermo-bidynamic Origin of Bisexual Differentiation in Protozoa,", undated (Box 13, Folder 136)
    - Chapter III, "The Origin of Metazoan Differentiation and Organization and its Malignant Differentiation and Disorganization,", undated (Box 13, Folder 137)
    - Chapter IV, "Ontogeny of Bisexual Differentiation in Man,", undated (Box 13, Folder 138)
    - Chapter IV, "Thermo-bidynamic Origin and Evolution of Bisexual and Somatic Differentiation in Protozoa,", undated (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - Chapter V, "Bisexual Social Adaptability in Mammals,", undated (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Chapter V, "Evolution of Bisexual and Somatic Differentiation of Chromosomes,", undated (Box 13, Folder 141)
    - Chapter VI, "Social Sexual Behavior of Infrahuman Primates,", undated (Box 13, Folder 142)
    - Chapter VII, "Comparative Primate Attitudinal Characteristics,", undated (Box 13, Folder 143)
    - Chapter VIII, "Phylogenetic Origins of Human Social Sexual Traits in Lower Primates,", undated (Box 13, Folder 144)
    - Chapter IX, "Prenatal Stage of Development of Motility and Sensitivity,", undated (Box 13, Folder 145)
    - Chapter X, "Nursling or Parasitic Stage of Postnatal Development of Attitude,", undated (Box 13, Folder 146)
    - Chapter XI, "The Influence of Excretory Organs and Functions and their Social Conditioning upon the Infantile Organization of Attitude,", undated (Box 13, Folder 147)
    - Chapter XII, "The Influence of Social Conditioning of Oral Alimentary Functioning upon Attitudinal Organization in the Infant,", undated (Box 13, Folder 148)
    - Chapter XIIa, "The Influence of Detention upon the Personality in Childhood,", undated (Box 13, Folder 149)
    - Chapter XIII, "Influence upon the Child's Attitude of Emergence of Genital Erotism and its Social Conditioning,", undated (Box 13, Folder 150)